<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0"
  xml:id="Lupack-Charlemagne-Export-05-Siege-Intro-tei">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Introduction to The Siege of Milan</title>
        <author>Lupack, Alan</author>
        <sponsor>The University of Rochester</sponsor>
        <sponsor>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</sponsor>
        <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
        <funder>The University of Rochester</funder>
        <funder>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Conrath, Ryan</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Delcourt, Steffi</persName>
          <resp from="2025-08" to="2025-09">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-07" to="2025-08">Collected metadata</resp>
          <resp from="2025-05" to="2025-07">Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-09">Encoded TEI</resp>
          <resp from="2025-07" to="2025-08">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp from="2025-05" to="2025-08">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-05" to="2025-07">Entered corrections for print edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-05" to="2025-08">Formatted for XML export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-09">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Johnson-Olin, Martha M.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Kephart, Daniel</persName>
          <resp from="2023-11" to="2023-11">Collected metadata</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>McShane, Kara L.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Peck, Russell A.</persName>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Roth, Aaron</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Encoded in TEI in 2025</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>The Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.sas.rochester.edu/eng/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://teams-medieval.org/about/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <distributor>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</distributor>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Downloading shall be restricted to one copy for private use.</p>
        </availability>
        <date/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s">The Middle English Text Series</title>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Rita Copeland</persName>
          <orgName>University of Texas</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas G. Hahn</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Lisa J. Kiser</persName>
          <orgName>Ohio State University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Russell A. Peck</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>General Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas H. Seiler</persName>
          <orgName>Western Michigan University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>R. A. Shoaf</persName>
          <orgName>University of Florida</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Bonnie Wheeler</persName>
          <orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Unknown</author>
            <editor>Lupack, Alan</editor>
            <title>Three Middle English Charlemagne Romances</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace>
              <date>1990</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Middle English Texts Series offers a diverse and representative array of literary
          texts that medieval readers in the present-day British Isles would have encountered
          between the twelfth and sixteenth centuries. It is committed to making available both
          affordable print and open access editions to scholars, teachers, and students of the
          Western Middle Ages. In its digital publications, the series prioritizes a user-friendly
          interface and viewing options, multiple downloadable formats, enhanced searchability and
          filtering, and accessibility to the widest possible range of users.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>METS takes as its mission the creation of affordable editions that would pass scrutiny
          from the most demanding expert, yet would prove comprehensible, and even enticing, to
          someone who had never read Middle English before. This agenda dictates that METS
          publications offer not a critical edition reflecting all surviving manuscripts, and
          certainly not a diplomatic edition, but a best-text edition, informed by the notes and
          apparatus of earlier editions (where these exist), and by substantive variants from other
          manuscript witnesses. Transcriptions of Middle English texts are lightly modernized to
          ensure a smooth reading experience, while non-English texts preserve both the original
          language and a modern English translation in facing-page format. Each edition offers
          expert assistance with language and lexicon, providing glosses alongside the text(s),
          textual and explanatory notes, elucidation of unfamiliar contexts and traditions, and
          thematic and interpretive possibilities. All editions feature general introductions that
          set the edited text within its own time, place, and traditions, and link it to ancestor,
          congener, and successor materials. All publications contain comprehensive, current
          bibliographies of pertinent scholarship and criticism. House style is adapted from the <hi
            rend="italic">Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p>
        <correction>
          <p>This text may include corrections made after the original edition went to press in
            order to correct errors and improve glosses. For a full list of editorial and
            typographical corrections made to this edition, please view its correction log on
            Github:
            https://github.com/mets-editions/lupack-charlemagne/blob/main/lupack-charlemagne-export-corrections-log.xlsx</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
      <schemaRef url="https://metseditions.org/schema/mets-editions.xsd"/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English, Modern (1500-present)</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>First edition published in 1990</change>
      <change>Encoded in HTML</change>
      <change>Entered editorial corrections in 2025</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <anchor xml:id="Lupack-Charlemagne-Export-05-Siege-Intro"/>
      <div type="text">
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="1"><hi rend="italic">The Sege of Melayne</hi> is found in the
          British Museum manuscript Additional 31042 (fols. 66b–79b). Referred to as the London
          Thornton manuscript, it is one of two collections of medieval writings known to have been
          copied by Robert Thornton of East Newton in Yorkshire. (The other is the Lincoln Cathedral
          manuscript 91, commonly referred to as the Thornton manuscript.) The British Museum
          manuscript dates from about 1450, though the poem itself was probably written some time in
          the second half of the fourteenth century. The poem is written in a northern dialect.
          Features of this dialect include the present participle in -<hi rend="italic">and(e)</hi>
          rather than -<hi rend="italic">ing</hi> (as in ‘gronande’ and ‘spekande’); the third
          person plural of the present tense in -<hi rend="italic">es</hi> or -<hi rend="italic"
            >is</hi> (as in ‘men that luffes’ and ‘knyghtis bledis’); third person plural pronouns
          in <hi rend="italic">th</hi>- (as in ‘thay’ and ‘tham’); and particularly northern forms
          such as ‘till’ (for ‘to’), ‘sall’ (for ‘shall’) and ‘solde’ (for ‘should’).</p>
        <p style="body" n="1"><hi rend="italic">The Sege of Melayne</hi> is fragmentary, the romance
          ending in the manuscript just as the French forces are besieging Milan and, surely, just
          before they capture the city C with, undoubtedly, a good deal of heroics by Archbishop
          Turpin. The poem is written in a twelve-line stanza rhyming <hi rend="italic"
            >aabccbddbeeb</hi>, though there are places where the rhyme scheme is not perfectly
          maintained.</p>
        <p style="body" n="2"><hi rend="italic">The Sege of Melayne</hi> is considered part of the
          Otinel (or Otuel) group of Charlemagne romances. Otinel is a Saracen knight who, like
          Ferumbras, is converted after a fierce battle with one of Charlemagne’s Peers, in this
          case Roland. The combat itself is described in the Middle English poems <hi rend="italic"
            >Otuel</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Otuel and Roland</hi>. Neither the combat nor even the
          character of Otuel appears in this poem as it has come down to us, but it is classified
          with the Otinel romances because only in these is Garcy the ruler of Lombardy.</p>
        <p style="body" n="3">But perhaps more interesting than its place in a cycle of romances is
          the fact that there is no known source for <hi rend="italic">The Sege of Melayne</hi>.
          Dieter Mehl has suggested that the poem may have ‘originated in England’ (p. 153). The
          conjecture is plausible because, more than any other Charlemagne romance, <hi
            rend="italic">The Sege of Melayne</hi> is a poem about a religious struggle rather than
          a glorification of the military prowess of the French king and his warriors. There is a
          sense that God, not Charlemagne, is directing the action and working through his minister,
          Turpin. As W. R. J. Barron observes,</p>
        <quote>the focus of interest has shifted so that the religious theme of defense of the faith
          dominates almost to the exclusion of the feudal theme of conflicting loyalties, while the
          rare miraculous interventions of the early <hi rend="italic">chansons</hi> now rival the
          military action in importance. (p. 97)</quote>
        <p style="bodysubsection" n="1">It is a vision in which an angel appears to Charlemagne and
          gives him a sword that inspires the holy war against the Saracens. And throughout the
          poem, God assists those fighting the Saracens in symbolic and real ways, so much so that
          ‘the romantic story-material is . . . given a strictly religious interpretation and is
          often embellished in the manner of Saints’ legends’ (Mehl, p. 156). Richard of Normandy,
          mortally wounded himself, is comforted by a vision of the slain French knights being led
          to heaven. When the Sultan Arabas tries to show the powerlessness of the God of the
          Christians by burning a crucifix, not only does it not burn but a fire flashes forth and
          blinds the Saracens, giving the French captives time to slay Arabas and to escape on
          horses miraculously provided for them (horses which equally miraculously disappear when
          the knights have reached safety).</p>
        <p style="body" n="4">Central to the shift towards a religious focus is the character of
          Bishop Turpin. Although the term may seem alien to medieval romance, <hi rend="italic">The
            Sege of Melayne</hi> borders on being a character study. Turpin is pictured as an
          unswerving defender of the faith. He demands high standards and correct action from those
          around him and even more from himself. Nor is he afraid to use the spiritual or political
          power of his religious position. When he hears how Roland’s forces have been defeated by
          the Saracens, he assembles the clergy of the realm and leads them in the vanguard of an
          attack on their enemy. He curses Ganelon for his bad advice and when Charlemagne,
          following Ganelon’s counsel, refuses to lead the forces against the Saracens, Turpin
          excommunicates Charlemagne and declares him an enemy of God and, in effect, a coward.
          Turpin is ready to fight Charlemagne at the very moment of this confrontation. They are
          restrained by the lords of the land, but Turpin threatens to besiege Paris and to burn and
          raze the city. When Turpin assembles his troops before the city, Charlemagne is forced to
          relent and ask forgiveness from the Archbishop.</p>
        <p style="body" n="5">In addition to this major conflict, there are some small touches that
          make the character of Turpin interesting. When he hears of the defeat of the French
          forces, he says, in a passage almost reminiscent of Laban’s complaints against his gods in
            <hi rend="italic">The Sowdone of Babylon</hi>, that Mary is to blame for the loss of the
          French lives and tells her that if she had not been born (and thus had not brought Christ
          and his religion into the world), those good men would not have died. He is so preoccupied
          with the disaster that when he encounters Charlemagne he doesn’t even greet him, a small
          detail that suggests Turpin’s single-minded dedication to his cause.</p>
        <p style="body" n="6">When Turpin and Charlemagne return to avenge the loss, the Archbishop
          once again displays unwavering dedication to the struggle and becomes the voice of
          conscience reminding others of their duty. Turpin’s own squire stops to despoil the body
          of a Saracen named Arabant, whom the Archbishop has slain. But his master tells him that
          he should not be worrying about gold when there are more Saracens to kill. He beats the
          squire with his sword to make him drop his loot and return to the battle.</p>
        <p style="body" n="7">Perhaps the most impressive and revealing action taken by Turpin is
          his refusal to allow any attempts to treat his wounds until the city of Milan is
          recaptured. Earlier, he reminded Charlemagne of the suffering of Christ and berated him
          for being unwilling to suffer in Christ’s cause. Turpin himself shows no such
          unwillingness. Twice wounded, he looks to Christ’s example: ‘He askede no salve to His
          sare, / Ne no more sall I this tyde’ (ll. 1346–47). Despite his wounds he encourages
          Charlemagne to attack a greatly superior force. And though the manuscript breaks off
          before the fall of the city, there can be no doubt that Turpin honored his vow not to
          accept treatment or to eat or drink until Milan was taken.</p>
        <p style="body" n="8">By giving such a clear picture of a man devoted to a cause, <hi
            rend="italic">The Sege of Melayne</hi> presents an interesting variation on the usual
          themes of the Charlemagne romances. Though containing a number of traditional motifs, such
          as Ganelon’s treachery, Charlemagne’s conflict with one of his Peers, and the battles
          between large numbers of troops, <hi rend="italic">The Sege of Melayne</hi> achieves some
          originality through its emphasis on Turpin as the military, political, spiritual and moral
          center of the poem.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
