<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0"
  xml:id="Lupack-Charlemagne-Export-08-Ralph-Intro-tei">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Introduction to The Tale of Ralph the Collier</title>
        <author>Lupack, Alan</author>
        <sponsor>The University of Rochester</sponsor>
        <sponsor>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</sponsor>
        <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
        <funder>The University of Rochester</funder>
        <funder>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Conrath, Ryan</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Delcourt, Steffi</persName>
          <resp from="2025-08" to="2025-09">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-07" to="2025-08">Collected metadata</resp>
          <resp from="2025-05" to="2025-07">Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-09">Encoded TEI</resp>
          <resp from="2025-07" to="2025-08">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp from="2025-05" to="2025-08">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-05" to="2025-07">Entered corrections for print edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-05" to="2025-08">Formatted for XML export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-09">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Johnson-Olin, Martha M.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Kephart, Daniel</persName>
          <resp from="2023-11" to="2023-11">Collected metadata</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>McShane, Kara L.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Peck, Russell A.</persName>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Roth, Aaron</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Encoded in TEI in 2025</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>The Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.sas.rochester.edu/eng/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://teams-medieval.org/about/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <distributor>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</distributor>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Downloading shall be restricted to one copy for private use.</p>
        </availability>
        <date/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s">The Middle English Text Series</title>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Rita Copeland</persName>
          <orgName>University of Texas</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas G. Hahn</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Lisa J. Kiser</persName>
          <orgName>Ohio State University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Russell A. Peck</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>General Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas H. Seiler</persName>
          <orgName>Western Michigan University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>R. A. Shoaf</persName>
          <orgName>University of Florida</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Bonnie Wheeler</persName>
          <orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Unknown</author>
            <editor>Lupack, Alan</editor>
            <title>Three Middle English Charlemagne Romances</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace>
              <date>1990</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Middle English Texts Series offers a diverse and representative array of literary
          texts that medieval readers in the present-day British Isles would have encountered
          between the twelfth and sixteenth centuries. It is committed to making available both
          affordable print and open access editions to scholars, teachers, and students of the
          Western Middle Ages. In its digital publications, the series prioritizes a user-friendly
          interface and viewing options, multiple downloadable formats, enhanced searchability and
          filtering, and accessibility to the widest possible range of users.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>METS takes as its mission the creation of affordable editions that would pass scrutiny
          from the most demanding expert, yet would prove comprehensible, and even enticing, to
          someone who had never read Middle English before. This agenda dictates that METS
          publications offer not a critical edition reflecting all surviving manuscripts, and
          certainly not a diplomatic edition, but a best-text edition, informed by the notes and
          apparatus of earlier editions (where these exist), and by substantive variants from other
          manuscript witnesses. Transcriptions of Middle English texts are lightly modernized to
          ensure a smooth reading experience, while non-English texts preserve both the original
          language and a modern English translation in facing-page format. Each edition offers
          expert assistance with language and lexicon, providing glosses alongside the text(s),
          textual and explanatory notes, elucidation of unfamiliar contexts and traditions, and
          thematic and interpretive possibilities. All editions feature general introductions that
          set the edited text within its own time, place, and traditions, and link it to ancestor,
          congener, and successor materials. All publications contain comprehensive, current
          bibliographies of pertinent scholarship and criticism. House style is adapted from the <hi
            rend="italic">Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p>
        <correction>
          <p>This text may include corrections made after the original edition went to press in
            order to correct errors and improve glosses. For a full list of editorial and
            typographical corrections made to this edition, please view its correction log on
            Github:
            https://github.com/mets-editions/lupack-charlemagne/blob/main/lupack-charlemagne-export-corrections-log.xlsx</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
      <schemaRef url="https://metseditions.org/schema/mets-editions.xsd"/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English, Modern (1500-present)</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>First edition published in 1990</change>
      <change>Encoded in HTML</change>
      <change>Entered editorial corrections in 2025</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <anchor xml:id="Lupack-Charlemagne-Export-08-Ralph-Intro"/>
      <div type="text">
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="1">The story of <hi rend="italic">Rauf Coilyear</hi> has come down
          to us in an edition printed in 1572. No manuscript survives and only one copy (owned by
          the National Library of Scotland) of this earliest printed text exists. The poem is a late
          product of the movement known as the Alliterative Revival, a revival — or more likely the
          continuation of a tradition — of the use of alliterative verse that extends back to the
          Old English period. The poems written in alliterative verse employ alliteration as a
          controlling metrical device. As in Old English, lines are divided into two half-lines
          linked by similar initial sounds. Middle English alliterative verse does not follow
          strictly the rules of the Anglo-Saxon, but the basic metrical principles survive. While
          examples of Middle English alliterative verse can be found from the twelfth century on
          (Layamon’s <hi rend="italic">Brut</hi> being the prime example), from the middle of the
          fourteenth century well into the fifteenth, there is once again a widespread use of
          alliterative verse. Some of the greatest Middle English poems, including <hi rend="italic"
            >Sir Gawain and the Green Knight</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Piers Plowman</hi>, and the
          alliterative <hi rend="italic">Morte Arthure</hi> are products of this revival.</p>
        <p style="body" n="1">The romance was written in the latter part of the fifteenth century in
          a Scottish dialect and exhibits many of the characteristic traits of that dialect. In the
          present tense, both the third person singular and the third person plural are indicated by
          the ending -<hi rend="italic">is</hi> (as in ‘buik sayis’; ‘he rydis’; ‘menstrallis
          playis’; and ‘men that counteris’). The present participle is indicated by -<hi
            rend="italic">and</hi> rather than -<hi rend="italic">ing</hi> (as in ‘lykand’ and
          ‘walkand’). The pronoun ‘she’ appears as ‘scho’; and the third person plural pronoun has
          forms in <hi rend="italic">th</hi> (as in ‘them,’ where southern and central dialects
          would use ‘hem’). A number of other spellings and forms found in the poem are also typical
          of the Scottish dialect. The Old English long <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, which becomes <hi
            rend="italic">o</hi> in central and southern dialects, remains as <hi rend="italic"
            >a</hi> (as in ‘hame’ for ‘home’; ‘ga’ for ‘go’; and ‘sa’ for ‘so’). The <hi
            rend="italic">wh</hi> of other dialects appears as <hi rend="italic">quh</hi> (as in
          ‘quhair’ for ‘where’; ‘quhat’ for ‘what’; and ‘quhen’ for ‘when’). The <hi rend="italic"
            >sh</hi> of more southern dialects appears as <hi rend="italic">s</hi> in ‘sall’ (for
          ‘shall’), ‘suld’ (for ‘should’) and ‘salbe’ for (‘shall be’). Other typically Scottish
          forms include ‘schir’ for ‘sir’ and ‘till’ (occasionally) for ‘to.’</p>
        <p style="body" n="2"><hi rend="italic">Rauf Coilyear</hi> is written in the thirteen-line
          stanza used in such other alliterative poems as <hi rend="italic">Golagros and
            Gawaine</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Awntyrs of Arthure</hi>. The stanza generally
          contains nine long (four-stress) lines, each of which is governed by alliteration, and
          four shorter lines which may or may not alliterate. The stanza also has a rhyme scheme of
            <hi rend="italic">ababababcdddc</hi>. As in all alliterative verse, there is
          considerable use of formulaic phrases, phrases such as ‘proudest in pane’ or ‘with birny
          and brand,’ which are used repeatedly within alliterative poetry to satisfy the
          metrical/alliterative needs of a portion of a line. Despite the traditional nature of
          these recurring phrases, the poet has — as Elizabeth Walsh observes in her article on the
          poem — used alliterative formulas in such a way that they ‘can be said to have some
          significance in the poem as elements of characterisation and/or as relating to thematic
          content’ (p. 17).</p>
        <p style="body" n="3">The poet demonstrates his craftsmanship not only as an alliterative
          poet but also as the author of a Charlemagne romance. For here too, he has made use of the
          traditional with great skill. <hi rend="italic">Rauf Coilyear</hi> is one of those Middle
          English Charlemagne poems known as ‘detached romances.’ That is, it belongs neither to the
          Ferumbras nor the Otuel group. There is, in fact, no known source for this poem, though
          there are analogues to each of the two parts. As a number of critics have pointed out, the
          first part of the poem is a version of the king-in-disguise motif common in folklore. In
          England the motif goes back to a story told about Alfred the Great. (In her edition, Walsh
          refers to many other analogous stories.) The second part of the poem parodies, as Barron
          has observed, ‘the Christian-Muslim combats of <hi rend="italic">Otuel</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Firumbras</hi>’ (p. 181). These two parts are woven together only loosely
          by a developing line of action. More important is the thematic unity that links the two
          parts.</p>
        <p style="body" n="4">The first part of the poem treats the rough but sincere hospitality
          Charlemagne receives from the simple collier. The treatment is much rougher than that to
          which the King is accustomed. When Rauf and Charlemagne arrive at Rauf’s house and the
          guest stands aside to let his host enter first, Rauf accuses him of being discourteous and
          shoves him into the house, telling the King that he ought to ‘make me lord of my awin’ (l.
          128). Later, after another breach of courtesy, Rauf strikes the King and instructs him to
          do as Rauf tells him because it is his (Rauf’s) house. The King’s reactions show that he
          realizes he should have recognized the right of a man to rule in his own home.</p>
        <p style="body" n="5">Charlemagne’s failure, initially, to recognize Rauf’s preeminence is
          matched by a lack of recognition on Rauf’s part. He does not recognize (in the two senses
          of the word) the King. He does not know what his monarch looks like and so unquestioningly
          accepts a pseudonym as his real name, even when Rauf’s wife has difficulty in believing
          that their grand guest is ‘Wymond of the Wardrop’; and Rauf fails to observe the King’s
          laws, at least as regards hunting in the royal forests. Rauf’s lack of knowledge goes even
          further than not knowing what the King looks like. When invited to bring a load of coal
          for sale at court, Rauf admits that he has ‘na knawledge quhair the court lyis’ (l.
          246).</p>
        <p style="body" n="6">By having Rauf come to the court, the King begins his knightly
          education by having him recognize — in both senses — his ruler. But Charlemagne also wants
          Rauf to prove himself, to win his shoes. As Rauf rides out in quest of adventure, his
          awareness is again deficient. He cannot distinguish between the Saracen Sir Magog and Sir
          Roland whom he has previously challenged — even though Magog rides a camel instead of a
          horse. Upon learning that Magog is a Saracen, Rauf is overjoyed to be fighting for the
          faith.</p>
        <p style="body" n="7">When Roland rides up and interrupts the battle, he immediately
          recognizes Magog as an infidel and even comments on this recognition: ‘Thow art ane
          Sarasine, I se be my sicht’ (l. 871). Instead of wishing to fight Magog, Roland wants to
          convert him. Just as Rauf was taught to recognize a king in two senses, so he is taught to
          recognize a Saracen on two levels: first physically and then as a religiously errant soul
          to be saved. Roland shows Rauf that victory over Magog’s false faith is more important
          than victory over his person.</p>
        <p style="body" n="8">But even more transpires in this scene. When Roland interrupts the
          combatants and encourages Magog to convert, the Saracen refuses and wants to continue
          fighting. Roland points out the foolishness of this course of action and after being
          threatened again tells Magog that it is folly to enjoy worldly wealth now and to spend
          eternity in hell. But he seems to contradict himself when he offers the Saracen profit and
          pardon if he will convert. At least he is not wholly aware of the meaning of the words he
          has just spoken (in ll. 918–20). Thus Roland, like Rauf, needs to be made more aware of
          the true values his knighthood and religion stand for. Both can learn a lesson from the
          reaction of the Saracen who doesn’t care about riches but says that if ‘thy God be sa gude
          as I heir the say, / I will forsaik Mahoun’ (ll. 937–38). Magog thus becomes another agent
          in the education of a knight; and the tested Roland can learn from him as well as the
          untried Rauf can. Magog’s reply makes (or should make) both of them aware of the
          distinction between a faith based on personal gain and a faith based on love of God.</p>
        <p style="body" n="9">The author uses the debate surrounding the conversion as both a
          satiric comment on Roland’s failure in religious awareness and as the final phase of
          instruction for Rauf. The author has skillfully manipulated the Christian-Saracen conflict
          so that the verbal contest becomes more important than the martial.</p>
        <p style="body" n="10">The two parts of the poem are thus linked by the theme of recognition
          or awareness — on the political, religious and personal levels that must combine to make
          one a good knight or, we might say, a good person. (The blurring of the distinction is
          significant in this late poem where the heroic conventions of earlier romance and
          certainly of the <hi rend="italic">chansons de gestes</hi> are taken with a grain of
          salt.) The theme is evident from the very beginning of the poem: the storm in which
          Charlemagne loses his way is a perfect symbol for the lack of awareness that must be
          dispelled in the course of the romance.</p>
        <p style="body" n="11">Though the author makes a serious point, he does so through a comic
          tale. It would be a mistake to read <hi rend="italic">Rauf Coilyear</hi> without
          recognizing the humor involved in the harboring of a king by a simple collier. Many
          incidents contribute to this humor — from the slapstick buffeting of Charlemagne, the
          emperor instructed by a collier, to Roland’s mild annoyance at being sent out to watch the
          lonely road on a day that is supposed to be a holiday. The elements of parody contribute
          to the humor. The traditional fight with the Saracen turns into a religious debate. The
          King’s being separated from his followers has echoes of the separation of Charlemagne from
          his troops and his abandonment due to the treachery of Ganelon in <hi rend="italic">The
            Sowdone of Babylone</hi>. This lighthearted use of the Charlemagne material makes <hi
            rend="italic">Rauf Coilyear</hi> perhaps the best and certainly the most entertaining of
          the Middle English Charlemagne romances.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
